<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble vindication of the Commissioners of the General Assembly and their late proceedings in answer to the letter of the high and honourable court of Parliament, dated May 11 to the several Presbyteries in the Kingdom</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B20341</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10861901</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204823</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240887386</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4229B</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">10861901</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B20341)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204823)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1419:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble vindication of the Commissioners of the General Assembly and their late proceedings in answer to the letter of the high and honourable court of Parliament, dated May 11 to the several Presbyteries in the Kingdom</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: Edinb. 6. Iunii, 1648.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204823:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204823:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinb.</hi>
                  <date>6. <hi>Iunii,</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>The humble VINDICATION OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY AND Their late Proceedings, in Answer to the LETTER of the High and Honourable Court of PARLIAMENT, dated <hi>May</hi> 11. to the several Presbyteries in the Kingdom.</head>
            <p>ALthough we doubt not but the particular Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries will sufficiently return answer to the Parliaments Letter so far as concerneth them, (wherein divers Presbyteries have already given ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the rest) yet the chief purposes of that Letter reflecting all along upon our late proceedings, and the Letter being also Printed and published for common view and use; The great trust put upon us will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us to be silent in such a case. And the greater cause we have to vindicate our proceedings in this manner, because whilest we had just reason to expect from the Parliament a clear and reall satisfaction to our desires, seconded by so many Provinciall Synods, instead of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204823:2"/>such satisfaction, that Letter came abroad with many reflections upon our proceedings, neither was any thing hereof communicat or made known from their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships to us, that we might have been heard for clearing our own actions before the divulging and spreading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad of the Letter.</p>
            <p>To the Preface of the Letter we answer, that as it is too manifest how many and great scandals are thrown upon us and our proceedings by the favourers of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants and haters of Reformation and Presbyteriall Government; So we know not either among our selves, or in any Assemblies of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> any favourers of Sectaries, or haters of the Person of the King and of Monarchicall Government, who throw scandals upon the Parliaments actions; And if any shall by sufficient proof discover any such in this Kingdom, it will quickly appear how far the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of this Church (and we for our part) shal be from conniving at them or bearing with them: Yea the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Assembly and Commissioners have already de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared so much, and so often both for the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Monarchical Government in his Majesty and his posterity, and against Sectaries. And there hath been also so long and real proof both of the loyalty of this Reformed Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> to his Majesties Father and to himself, and of zeal in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Church Discipline against Sectaries (whereever any were found) that the world may bear witnesse with our Consciences of our integrity both in the one and in the other, although we should altogether hold our peace. Errour will sooner comply with errour then truth can, and favourers of Malignants have been and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204823:2"/>may again turn to be favourers of Sectaries, to serve their turn and save their interest for the time. For our part as we did before so we do still clearly and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously professe that we look upon Sectaries and Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants as enemies to be opposed, as rocks to be avoided on the right and left hands.</p>
            <p>We see no cause why the several Presbyteries need to be <hi>censured</hi> as they will answer to the great God not to suffer themselves to be possest with unjust and undeser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved prejudices against the Parliament &amp; their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; The fear of God, and conscience of their duty will keep them upon the one hand from unjust and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserved prejudices against their Lordships and their proceedings, and upon the other hand from obeying unjust Decrees, and complying with iniquity altho established by a Law.</p>
            <p>What their Lordships professe concerning their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of no earthly thing to their duties for Religion, and concerning their reall endeavours to satisfie the most tender consciences by their Lordships great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with our many desires; All this we leave to the searcher of the hearts, and tryer of the reins, who can and will judge thereof: This we can say for our selves, that to this day, we have not received a satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Answer from their Lordships unto any one of our desires presented to their Lordships for the safety and security of Religion, but under colour of yielding somewhat, our desires were more dangerously refused, then if they had been flatly rejected.</p>
            <p>If that which followeth in the Letter hold good, viz. <hi>That it cannot be by any with truth and justice alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged that their Lordships have in the least measure wronged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204823:3"/>or violated the true Priviledges and Liberties of the Church,</hi> we are greatly to be blamed and censured for complaining in one of our Papers to the Parliament that their Lordships have very much prejudiced the true priviledges and liberties of this Kirk, and for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testing (upon that occasion) against such preparatives, and for preservation of the liberties of the Kirk in time coming. But now how much truth and justice we had for the ground of our grievance and protestation, all who will not shut their eyes against the clear light may easily understand. For was it ever before heard or known, that any Parliament of this Kingdom did without the knowledge and consent of those who had for the time the trust of the publick affairs of the Kirk, determine, judge and declare, by an antecedent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, matters so highly concerning Religion, as these contained in the Parliaments late Declaration. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there are not only dangerous expressions concerning the Confession of Faith, Directory of Worship, and Presbyterial Government (as we have particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stanced in our late Declaration) but likewise in the close a strange and new sence put upon the Covenant and acts of General Assemblies, without so much as first consulting us concerning such a sence thereof, which might have been prevented if they had consulted us therein: Notwithstanding of all which the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being communicat to us from the High and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Parliament, and we having promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a speedy return thereto, which accordingly after eight days we performed, (the matter being copious) the Declaration was ordered by the Parliament to be printed, and the three demands contained therein sent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204823:3"/>away to <hi>England</hi> without staying a little for our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer (which we had let them know we were preparing) whereas a very short delay might have by the blessing of God brought unto their Lordships more light, and matter of second thoughts.</p>
            <p>We can as easily acquit our selves of any incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the unquestionable Rights of Parliament. We are obliged by Solemn Covenant to endeavour the preservation of the Rights and Priviledges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; And to encroach upon the same were indeed a hainous crime, wherewith if any shall reproach us, let them take heed what the ninth Command will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act of them: yet they who will remember how in all ages, the most faithfull servants of God have usually been traduced as troublers of, and encroachers upon the Rights of the Civill Magistrate, will not much marvail that what hath been is now.</p>
            <p>As to the three instances mentioned in the Letter, to prove that great encroachments are made upon their Lordships unquestionable Rights. First it is said, <hi>What can be more civill then to determine what Civil duties we ought to pay to our King, or what Civill powers he ought to be possessed of?</hi> We ask again whether in our late confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences with their Lordships concerning an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in War, there was any thing more proper to be insisted upon by us, then the securing of Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worldly interests, and particularly, that secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may be had from his Majestie for the point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion before his restitution to the exercise of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power? Must not duties to God (whereof the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204823:4"/>of Religion is a main one) have the supream and first place, duties to the King a subordinate and second place? Next as we have not determined what civill duties the Parliament ought to pay to the King, or what civill powers he ought to be possessed of; and as it is competent to the Parliament to Judge of Civil duties between the King and his People, in their own way; so can we not admit that it is proper and compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent only to them to judge of those duties; for the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the second table as wel as of the first, as namely, the duties between King and Subject, Parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Husbands and Wives, Masters and servants and the like, being contained in, and to be taught and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Word of God, are in that respect and so far as concerneth the point of conscience a subject of Ministeriall Doctrine, and in difficult cases a subject of cognizance, and judgement to the Assemblies of the Kirk. And here it is not to be passed that the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the large Confession of Faith, ratified by Acts of Parliament, did long since determine the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Kings and Subjects, The l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke whereof may be seen in the other Confessions of Faith of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches.</p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas it is said, <hi>Is there any other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in this Kingdom but that of the Parliament, and what flows from them, that can pretend Authoritative power in the choice of the Instruments and Managers of their publike Resolutions?</hi> We humbly ask, is there any Ecclesiasticall Authority within this Kingdom that hath pretended or doth pretend to such a power? for we know no such thing. An Authoritative power
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204823:4"/>and choice of the Instruments to be entrusted in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of Parliament and Armies, doth not belong unto us but unto the Parliament. Neverthelesse it was very competent for us among other things requ site for the safety and security of Religion and our Solemn Covenant, to represent to the Parliament the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications which we judged from Gods word to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary in such as are entrusted with the managing of so great Affairs, and so highly concerning our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Consciences; Which have had the more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to insist upon, for our own and others fatisfaction, we being desired to joyn and concur in the businesse. Suppose a Minister preaching before the Election of Magistrates (which is usuall) and shewing from the Word of God the Qualifications requisite in Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates and that none ought to be chosen but such as are so and so qualified; who will challenge such a Minister of assuming the Authoritative power of choosing Magistrates? And if the choosing of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Magistrates in Cities and Burghs contrary to the Rules and Qualifications of the Word, be sinfull and blame-worthie, how much more the committing of so great a publick trust in Committees and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to divers not Qualified with the necessary Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications.</p>
            <p>To the third Instance, which asketh, <hi>Is it a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for the Dispute of Church Judicatories, whether his Majestie hath a Negative voice in Parliament, or not?</hi> We answer, so far as the Scriptures of the Old or New Testament hold forth any light to us, what Power is due, and what is not due to Kings, it well
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204823:5"/>agreeth with our places and callings, to communicate such light to others as we see need. We know no Church Judicatorie that hath disputed whether his Majestie hath a negative voice in Parliament; but we had just reason to supplicate the Parliament that they might not interest themselves in any quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell for his Majesties Negative voice, because of the great dangers which may thereby come to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not onely by future disappointments of the so much desired settlement of Church affairs, but by quarrelling the Solemn League and Covenant it self, and the begun Reformation and Uniformity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which hath been purchased with so much pains, hazards, losses and sufferings.</p>
            <p>And now we shall take all these three instances joyntly, and make this further answer to them all. First, although the points had been meerly civill, yet by the Confession of Faith agreed upon by the Assembly of Divines at <hi>Westminster</hi> and approved by the Generall Assembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> as sound and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox as the Act more particularly beareth, we are allowed to apply our selves to the Parliament by way of humble supplication even in Civill matters, The Parliament also having in their Declaration expressed their desires and resolutions, that the said Confession of Faith be confirmed and established, have upon the matter allowed us to supplicate their Lordships con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning such things. Next we say, that in all the three instances which are given, our supplications and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires were to avert what we justly conceived to be destructive to Religion: We hope no man will have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204823:5"/>the face to say that the Assemblies of the Church may supplicat against dangers of Religion which fall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the first table, but not against dangers of Religion which fall within the second Table, or that they may supplicat against dangers of Religion arising from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, but not against dangers of Religion in which his Majesty is any way concerned, or which flow from a bad choice of the Instruments and managers of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick resolutions.</p>
            <p>The Episcopall disease of medling with Civill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs we trust through Gods mercy neither hath nor shall have any place among the Ministry of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, who by their Nationall Covenant abjured the Civill places and power of Kirk-men. Only we shall desire it may be remembred that there were other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopal diseases and distempers beside this, as namely, encroaching upon the liberties and priviledges of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Assemblies, the forcing of the consciences of Gods people, and persecuting such who could not in conscience obey. Wherefore it is necessar that all the Episcopal evils and disorders be carefully avoided. And as we do not doubt the ensuing General Assembly wil do what shall be fit for them to prevent the vilifying and contemning the Authority of Parliament, if it be found in danger to be vilified, so we humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they will not be unmindfull to prevent the vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and contemning of the authority of their own Commissioners.</p>
            <p>The following clause in the Letter putteth over to the General Assembly any of the Ministery, <hi>who shall offer to stir up the Subiects of this Kingdom to disobey or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204823:6"/>deny to give civill obedience to their Laws, it being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly provided by the second and third Acts of King</hi> James 6. <hi>his</hi> 8. <hi>Parliament in</hi> Anno 1584. <hi>that none of his Majesties Subjects under the pain of Treason impugne the Authority of Parliament.</hi> Where first we shall desire that two known distinctions, which in this passage of the Letter seem either to be confounded or forgotten, may be remembred. Civill obedience to Acts of Parliament is either in things unlawfull and contrary to the Word of God, or in things lawfull and right. In the former case it is a sin to obey: in the latter case, a sin not to obey. Again the Authority of Parliament is one thing, an Act of Parliament another thing; We do still acknowledge their Authority when we obey not this or that Act. And whatsoever be the Treason of impugning the Authority of Parliament, it can be no Treason to obey God rather then man: Neither did the Generall Assembly of <hi>Glasgow</hi> 1638. and such as were active for the Covenant at that time commit any Treason when they impugned Episcopacy and <hi>Perth</hi> Articles, although ratified and strengthened by Acts of Parliament and standing Laws then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repealed.</p>
            <p>As to the two Acts cited in the Letter, if the Order of the Printed Acts be followed, the third hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it of what it is cited for, neither know we for what use it can be cited and applied, except to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridging of the Liberties of Ecclesiasticall Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; for it dischargeth all Judicatories and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Conventions and Assemblies Ecclesiasticall, without his Majesties speciall licence and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204823:6"/>which how contrary it is to the word of God, to the example of the primitive Church, to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of sound Divines, to the Liberties of this Kirk, and to our Solemn Covenants, is more manifest then to need that we should insist upon it. But if the Order of the unprinted Acts be followed, the second of these Acts doth not mention the Authority of Parliament, but of his Majesty and his Counsell: However we are heartily sorry for the citation of the Acts of that Parliament, a Parliament which rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced Episcopacy, and so made defection from the Nationall Covenant sworn three years before: For Captain <hi>James Stewart</hi> then Earl of <hi>Arran</hi> and Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, and the few Prelates of that time contrived and procured such Acts of Parliament as might serve their ends. The same Acts were alledged and urged by his Majesties Commissioner in <hi>Anno</hi> 1638. for Episcopacy, whereunto this Answer was made at that time, <hi>The Acts of Parliament,</hi> 1584. <hi>are of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall natures, but they were protested against by the Ministers of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>in name of the Kirk of</hi> Scotland <hi>at the Market Crosse of</hi> Edinburgh <hi>when they were Proclaimed, and as they were made in that time which was called the houre of darknesse of this Kirk Tyranized over by the Earl of</hi> Arran, <hi>so are they repealed,</hi> 1542. Cap. 114. It is not to be forgotten, That after the making of those Acts of Parliament they were so generally disliked by all good men, that the chief Courtiers of that time thought it necessary to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy Master <hi>Patrick Adamson,</hi> a chiefe diviser of these Acts to make a Declaration of the meaning thereof in his Majesties Name, which he accordingly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204823:7"/>performed. Concerning which Declaration the said Master <hi>Patrick</hi> pretended Archbishop of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> did afterwards in his renunciation make this Confession. <hi>As where I am burthened to be the set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forth of a Book called the Kings Declaration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the whole Order of the Kirk is condemned and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, I protest before God, that so I was commanded to write the same by the Chancellour for the time, but chiefly by the Secretary, another great Courtier who him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self penned the second Act of Parliament, concerning the Power and Authority of Judicatory to be absolute in the Kings Power, and that it should not be lawfull for any subject to reclaim from the same, under the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the Act which I suppose was Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beside that Declaration his Majestie himself ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received a supplication from divers well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Ministers with their Animadversions upon the said Acts of Parliament, did pen with his own hand another Declaration of the meaning thereof: But by both those Declarations it may be easily understood that the said Acts were intended for innovating and changing the Government and Discipline of this Kirk, for setting up Bishops, and for suppressing the best Ministers, and accordingly they were made use of afterwards for the ground of a charge against the Ministers that were banished.</p>
            <p>It shall not be amisse here to insert that part of the Ministers Animadversions (given in to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty at that time) which concerneth the second Act of that Parliament, the words are these. <hi>As concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204823:7"/>
               <q>
                  <hi>the second Act the narration thereof appeareth to be slanderous against some of the Ministry which we would wish to be reformed or otherwise conceived, except the truth thereof were verified. And as to the substance of the act it self, it attributeth to your Majestie a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power of Judgement not onely upon the persons of your Subjects, but also in all matters wherein they or any of them shall be apprehended, summoned, or charged, &amp;c. Which appeareth to be very strange, the like whereof we hear not to have been practised in any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Common-wealth, and cannot stand with the word of God, for although the persons of men are subject to your Majesty and Civill Judges when they offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst your Laws, yet matters Ecclesiasticall and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conscience, no Christian Prince can justly claim nor ever claimed to himself such power to Judge. Seeing the Prince in this behalf is a member of the Kirk, and Jesus Christ onely the head, who only hath power to give Laws in matters of Conscience, and so said the godly</hi> Ambrose, Imperator bonus intra Ecclesiam non su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra Ecclesiam est; <hi>And to confound the Jurisdiction, civill and Ecclesiastical, is that thing wherein men of all good Judgements have justly found fault with, in the Pope of Rome, who claimeth to himself the power of both the swords, which is as great a fault to a Civill Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate to claim and usurp, and especially to iudge upon Doctrine, Errors and Haeresies, he not being placed in Ecclesiasticall function to interpret the Scriptures, the warrants hereof out of the word of God we are likewise to bring forth.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto we shall adde a passage out of the recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Master <hi>Patrick Adamson</hi> subscribed with his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204823:8"/>hand before famous witnesses and exhibit to the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Fyffe.</hi> The passage is this. <q>
                  <hi>There are contained in that second Act of Parliament divers others false intentions for to defame the Ministrie and to bring the Kirk of God in hatred and envy with their Prince and Nobility, burdening and accusing the Ministers falsly of Sedition and other crimes whereof they were innocent, (as likewise it is written in the samen Act and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof that Soveraign and Supream power per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the King in matters Ecclesiasticall, which is worthy to be condemned, and not to be contained among Christian Acts, where the power of the Word is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolled above all the power of Princes, and to be brought under subiection to the samen.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The words of the second Printed Act cited o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the third unprinted (so far as concerneth the purpose of the Letter) we finde to be thus: <hi>That none of his Lieges or Subiects presume or take upon hand to impugne the dignity and the Authority of the saids three Estates, or to seek or procure the innovation or dimunition of the Power and Authority of the same three estates or any of them in time coming under the pain of Treason.</hi> These words we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive as they relate to the constitution of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament made of the three Estates and to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thereof, being in that manner constituted, not to the obedience of their particular Acts, so if they be urged and pressed according to the meaning and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Act before declared, they will conclude under Treason all who impugne the power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Bishops, Abbots and Pryors as the third Estate of Parliament.</p>
            <p>To the conclusion of the Letter we shall need to say
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204823:8"/>but little, having already in other papers expressed our selves fully concerning the unsatisfactorines of their Lordships Declaration, and the unlawfulnesse of the present engagement; Which although it be pretended to be the same cause for which this Kingdom hath done and suffered so much, yet if it be remembred that the Kirks desires for the point of Religion are not granted, that the wel-affected who were most zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in the cause from the beginning are generally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this engagement, that it is carried on by such as were for the most part dis-affected to the Cause in the beginning, and were against the former expeditions; that the Publick affairs are entrusted into many new hands, such as we cannot be confident of; These and the like considerations will quickly make it appear that the cause is not the same, but hugely different from what it was, and that the same grounds and principles which made us active in furthering the former expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hinder us from furthering this.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:204823:9"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:204823:9"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edinb:</hi>
                  <date>10. <hi>Iunii</hi> 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <head>The humble ADVICE AND PETITION OF THE COMMISSION of the GENERAL ASSEMBLY, To the Honourable ESTATES of <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHile we were about the preparing of our thoughts concerning the unsatisfactorinesse of a Paper communicat unto us from your Lordships upon <hi>Wednesday,</hi> being a draught of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204823:10"/>from the Parliament to the several Petitions of Presbyteries, Synods and Shires tendered to them: There was a motion made unto us from your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships by the Lord <hi>Ley</hi> and the Laird of <hi>Armstoun,</hi> to wave a particular return unto that Paper, seeing it wes not to be looked upon as the sense or minde of the Parliament, in respect that before the Parliament had taken it into debate or consideration they did think fit to communicat it to this Commission; and withall to desire that the Commission would be pleased to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Parliament their advise, concerning the security of Religion in answer to the several Petitions presented to the Parliament of late from Synods, Presbyteries and Shires: Unto which motion we make this humble return.</p>
            <p>For the first part of the motion; We are resolved to lay aside the consideration of that Paper, and to make no Representation of our thoughts thereupon, if your Lordships be pleased to make no further use thereof.</p>
            <p>As for the other part of the motion, calling for our advise concerning an Answer to the Petitions presen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from several Shires, Presbyteries and Synods unto the Parliament: Although we humbly conceive your Honours may clearly perceive what is our judgement by our Papers presented to your Lordships from time to time; yet being required we shall again faithfully and freely tender this our humble advise.</p>
            <p>We call to record the searcher of all hearts, the Iudge of the world, that our not concurring with your Lordships proceedings hitherto, hath not flowed from want of zeal against Sectaries, for the suppression
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204823:10"/>of whom, and for the advancement of the work of Reformation, we are ready to hazard all in a lawfull way; Nor from any remissnes in that which concerns his Majesties true Honour and happiness, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of Monarchical Government in him and his Posterity, nor from any want of tenderness of the priviledges of Parliament; nor from want of Simpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie with our afflicted and oppressed Brethren in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> nor from partiall or sinistrous respect to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or person whatsoever within the Kingdom; But from meer tenderness in the point of security of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the Union between the Kingdoms, and from the unsatisfactoriness of the grounds of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Declaration, as hath been expressed more at length in our Representation: Notwithstanding your Lordships, to our very great grief, have proceeded to a Levie, whereby most heavy burthens and pressures have been laid upon many faithfull Covenanters most forward in all former expeditions, and averse from this, only for want of satisfaction concerning the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity and lawfulnesse thereof promised in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships late Declaration, but not as yet performed.</p>
            <p>It is therefore our humble advise that the abovemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Petitions being so just in themselves, and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the grounds aforesaid, as they ought in equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to have been granted, so they ought yet to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the securing Religion, staying the present Levy; and according to our former desires by essaying Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with <hi>England,</hi> applications to his Majestie and all other fair and amicable wayes for removing the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between the Kingdoms, before sending any forces to <hi>England</hi> or any other way of engagement in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204823:11"/>War. And least the taking of <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carlile</hi> (which is so scandalous to this Nation) be looked upon by <hi>England</hi> as a breach of union on your part; That your Lordships would be pleased to make it appear, that neither the Parliament, or any of your number have had any accession to the surprisall or supplying of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hese Towns, nor shall have any correspondence or complyance with these who have been actors therein.</p>
            <p>We do also conceive it necessary for satisfaction of the Petitioners, That his Majesties late Concessions and offers concerning Religion may by your Lordships directly and positively be declared unsatisfactory to this present Parliament.</p>
            <p>That albeit we would not be understood, as if we have had, or have, any thoughts of declining the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing of his Majesty to the same condition he wes in, by the agreement of both Kingdoms when he was taken away by a party of the Army under Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> that both Kingdoms may freely make their Applications to him; yet your Lordships would be pleased to Declare, That there shall be no engagement for restoring his Majesty to one of his Houses with Honour, Freedom and safety (which doth amount to no lesse then the restitution of his Majesty to the exercise of his Royall power, for the reasons holden forth in our late Representation never yet answered) before security and assurance be had from his Majesty by his solemn Oath under his hand and Seal; That he shall for Himself and his Successors, consent and agree to Acts of Parliament, enjoyning the League and Covenant, and fully establishing Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Directory of worship, and Confession of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204823:11"/>Faith in all his Majesties Dominions, and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty shall never make opposition to any of these, or endeavour any change thereof.</p>
            <p>That your Lordships will make it appear that you mean to be far from interesting your selves in any quarrell for his Majesty, that may put in his Majesties hands such power, as may not only bring the by gone proceedings of both Kingdoms in the League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in question, but also for the time to come make void all the Authority of Parliaments though proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never so rightly in reference to Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>That a clear and direct course be laid down and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared not only to associate nor joyn in Counsels or Forces with the Popish, Prelatical or Malignant party, but also to oppose and effectually endeavour to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse all such of them as have already risen or shall hereafter rise in Arms upon whatsomever pretence, as enemies to the Cause and Covenant on the one hand, as well as Sectaries on the other.</p>
            <p>That nothing be done in carying on the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may break the union of the Kingdoms, or may discourage or disoblige the Presbyterian party in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Because it is our grief, and the grief of all the Well-affected, that these who have been of constant and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven integrity in the Cause, and have been very instrumentall under God for our deliverance, should be forced for want of satisfaction to their consciences to leave the service; and that others who have not given constant proof of their integrity and faithfulnes, and against whom there is just cause of exception and jealousie, so that we cannot exhort our Flocks to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204823:12"/>confident of their fidelity; yea, and divers that have been in reall opposition to the Cause, are entrusted with the managing your Lordships publike resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: That therefore your Lordships will be pleased in your wisdom to provide a timous remedy herein.</p>
            <p>That there be no Engagement, without a Solemn Oath, wherein the Kirk may have the same interest which they had in the solemn League and Covenant, the Cause being the same.</p>
            <p>As we doe humbly insist with your Lordships for satisfaction to our former desires expressed in our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Papers, so it is our humble petition to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, That in such things as have been ordained by your Lordships and put in execution by your Order contrary to some of these desires, some effectuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy may be found out by your Lordships wisdome and goodnesse for the help thereof; That all who since the beginning of this Levie, through tendernesse of conscience, have suffered any wayes, may be repaired, all unusuall and grievous courses impoverishing good people and utterly disabling them to subsist, may be hereafter avoided; and the intolerable insolencie, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaness, blasphemies, &amp; manifold outrages that of late have appeared in the Souldiers, may be severely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed and repressed; That no Ordinance nor Order may issue from your Lordships in prejudice of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Kirk, and of the free exercise of any part of the Ministeriall calling, all which they have from Jesus Christ the only Head and Lawgiver in his Kirk, and which your Lordsh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps are obliged by solemn oath in our Cov enants to maintain: And that as it is our grief, that whilst your Lordships have been seeking
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204823:12"/>our advice, you have been and are making grievous Acts, as we are informed; so we desire your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships in the fear of God to be wary of making or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining such Acts, and namely, That you put not the power of arbitrary Government in the hands of any intrusted by your Lordships, nor ordain any Oaths to be imposed or exacted, that may be snares to mens consciences.</p>
            <p>All which we seriously recommend to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships, as you desire not to provoke against your selves and your posterity the wrath of the most high God, and that the Lord should not avenge the quarrell of a broken Covenant upon the Parliament and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi> But if your Lordships shall be pleased to hearken to our humble advice, and to satisfie the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of the well-affected in the Kingdome to the work of Reformation, by granting their just desire; Your Honours shall be blessed of God, the Lord of the whole earth; the people of God shall blesse you in the name of the Lord, and blesse the Lord for you; You shall bind up the sores of this distressed and distracted Kingdom, endear the affections of all the wel-affected, disappoint the designes of the disaffected, and your Names shall be a praise unto the present and succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generations; And we shall poure out our suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations before him, who sitteth and judgeth among Gods, to endue your Lordships with the Spirit of counsel and of the fear of his Name, that your Resolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be rightly ordered and tend to his glory, the security of Religion, the honour and happinesse of the King and his posterity, and the peace and safety of the Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. KER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>